Guide to the Margherita Hamm, John R. McMahon and Eileen Douglas papers M2116
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Margherita Hamm, John R. McMahon and Eileen Douglas papers
1891-1945
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Michael Brown Rare Books
Hamm, Margherita Arlina, 1871-1907
McMahon, John R. (John Robert), 1875-
Douglas, Eileen, 1903-
M2116
1.251 Linear Feet (3 boxes and 1 map folder)
Content Description
The materials consists of 157 letters, 13 essays, 101 radio scripts, 1 book of poems, 66 photographs, 20 negatives, and approximately 89 pieces of various printed and manuscript ephemeral materials pertaining to the Hamm and McMahon families, all dated from 1891-1945.
Biographical / Historical
Margherita Arlina Hamm (1867-1907) married John R. McMahon (1875-1956) in 1902. Both were authors and journalists, and their daughter Arlina Douglas McMahon, a.k.a. Eileen Douglas, was a stage and radio actress and radio script writer.
General
Detailed biographies of Hamm, McMahon, and Douglas available upon request.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Stanford University Libraries in 2015.
Journalists.; Suffragists -- United States; Michael Brown Rare Books; Hamm, Margherita Arlina, 1871-1907; McMahon, John R. (John Robert), 1875-; Douglas, Eileen, 1903-
- Margherita Arlina Hamm - letters from publishers, 1893-1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Margherita Arlina Hamm - letters from mother, 1905-1907; letter to Aunt Isabel, May 12, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Margherita Arlina Hamm - essays - typescript and manuscript (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters by John R. McMahon as executor of Aunt Isabel's will, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letter to father from John R. McMahon, January 4, 1892, and to mother, April 9, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters from parents while in India to John R. McMahon and his brother, Charles, 1891-1895 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters to John R. McMahon including from publishers, bank, law offices, and personal letters from family members, 1901-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Poems of Margherita Arlina Hamm - contents from binder of John R. McMahon - typescript (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letters to Madre - Mrs. John R. McMahon (Beatrice) - from Me (Eileen Douglas) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Eileen Douglas - correspondence (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1901-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Eileen Douglas - newspaper clippings, including Fred Allen Show (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Margherita Arlina Hamm - agreements with publishers (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Margherita Arlina Hamm - biography for The National Cyclopedia of American Biography (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Ephemera pertaining to M. Hamm, including pamphlets, obituary of S. Fales, speeches of M. Hamm (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Susan L. McMahon and Laura A. McMahon - estate documents (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Indenture between Joseph Cummings and Deborah Cummings, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Mary Isabella Stearns - copy of Last will and testament (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Isaiah McMahon - naturalization document (Box 2, Folder 3)
- John R. McMahon - agreements with publishers, 1901-1907 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Ephemera: WOR programs, envelopes, newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Letters to Mr and Mrs. R. McMahon (John and Beatrice), 1931 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Eileen Douglas - radio scripts (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
- Eileen Douglas - radio scripts (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- Photographs, including extra Everglades photographs and negatives (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Glass negative - broken and unidentified (Box 3, Folder 4)
- John L. McMahon - Last will and testament, October 30, 1896 (Map-folder 4)
- Belinda Higgins - Indenture, September 19, 1857 (Map-folder 4)
- Joseph Cummings and Deborah S., wife - Indenture, March 10, 1856 (Map-folder 4)
- G. W. McMahon - Diploma from Genesee Wesleyan Seminary (Map-folder 4)
- Cotton's Weekly, June 2, 1910 (Map-folder 4)